<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief answer to a late discourse concerning the unreasonableness of a new separation</title>
            <author>Grascome, Samuel, 1641-1708?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41807</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1568</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26749</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09531515</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09531515</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43527</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41807)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43527)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1332:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief answer to a late discourse concerning the unreasonableness of a new separation</title>
                  <author>Grascome, Samuel, 1641-1708?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Samuel Granscome--NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Oaths (Canon law)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43527:1"/>
            <head>A brief Anſwer to a late Diſcourſe concerning <hi>The Unreaſonableneſs of a New Separation.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHether the Letter was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to, or feigned by our Author I know not, nor is it of any concern; either way it might give a fit Occaſion to ſtart the Queſtion: And he pretends a ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize to read that the Non-Swearers ſhould think themſelves bound to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate Communion, though he ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles with himſelf to think it poſſible, that thoſe who have expreſſed ſo great a Senſe of the Miſchief of it in others, ſhould be ſo ready to fall <hi>into it themſelves.</hi> But alas, he need not have been at that Pains if he <hi>had</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, That they do not <hi>fall,</hi> but are forced into it, as I ſhall preſently make appear. Indeed he ſeems to be troubled, for he tells us, That he ſoon apprehended the miſchievous Conſequence of a new Schiſm: And I wiſh he, and ſome others had been as Quick-ſighted in foreſeeing and preventing ſuch Cauſes, which una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidably produce ſuch Miſchiefs: But I find that ſome Men look one way, and ſome another; and ſome after they have done all the Miſchief they can, yet will not leave off that old ſtale Trick of wiping their Mouths, And ſaying they have done no Hurt.</p>
            <p>But the Wonder is, that Men ſhould be ſo Obſtinate, <hi>When the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is only about the Reſolution of a Caſe of Conſcience, wherein wiſe and good Men may eaſily differ.</hi> And is then a Caſe of Conſcience really ſo trivial a Thing? I had thought there was not any moral Action, and conſequently not any Duty of a Chriſtian, about which a Caſe of Conſcience might not one time or other ariſe; and may theſe then be determin'd either ways, becauſe wiſe and good Men may ſo eaſily differ: What is this but to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the very Nature of Good and Evil, or to make the bounds ſo move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, that we ſhall never know cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly where to find them. I ſhall readily grant, that when the matter is Dark and Intricate, we may well hope, that God will be merciful to a miſtaken Perſon; but if a Caſe of Conſcience ariſe, let Men differ as they pleaſe, he only determines right, who determines with the nature of the Thing; and he is only Safe, who follows that Determination. He that determines beſide, or againſt the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Thing, determins wrong, and in moral Actions he certainly doth ill, who follows ſuch determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, however merciful ſoever God upon other accounts may be to him. And this, Nature ſeems to have taught every Man; for why elſe ſhould all the Comforts of a Man's Soul ſo much depend upon the Satisfaction of his Conſcience, that he hath taken a right courſe: Whereas it were the eaſieſt matter in the World to ſatisfy Conſcience, if without much ado they might ſafely ſubmit to any De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination, which comes from a Man, who, for any Thing we know, may be Wiſe and Good. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whatſoever our Authour may think, I ſhall deſire him hencefor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:43527:2"/>
to ſpeak more reverendly of a Caſe of Conſcience, leſt he tempt a looſe World both to think and ſpeak meanly of our Employment.</p>
            <p>Well, a Caſe of Conſcience it is, though a Shriveled one; but the Oaths (ſaith he) are not made a Condition of Communion, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot be a ſufficient cauſe of Separation. Now I could have told him forty Things which they are not; and if he ſhould be out in that one, which he mentions, it would be very unlucky; and that he is ſo, I ſhall endeavour preſently in its proper place to prove. In the mean time I could tell him of a Man, who hath Diſcourſed much of Terms of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, who hath Quarrelled al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all, and yet never failed to comply with any that were ſet up; and it is hard to tye us up to that Man's Terms of Communion, which no Man living could ever yet learn what they were.</p>
            <p>But he tells us, That there is a difference between a <hi>Tender and a ſour Conſcience,</hi> and I doubt not, but in his Liberality he intended the <hi>ſour Conſcience</hi> for us; and he might have made it what he pleaſed when he was about it. But as I am well ſatisfied in my Conſcience (at leaſt as to my ſelf) that I have taken a ſafer courſe in this Matter to appear before the Tribunal of Heaven than our Jolly Swearers: So I will aſſure this Author, That if he have no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Phyſick than he Adminiſters in this Diſcourſe, he will never make a true Cure of any of thoſe Conſciences, which he is pleaſed to repreſent as Diſeaſed and Sowre; but perhaps the <hi>Sowreneſs</hi> may lie elſewhere, and ſome complain of the Light, when the fault is in the weakneſs of their Eyes.</p>
            <p>It is a wonderful Condeſcenſion in our Author, but to ſuppoſe, <hi>That thoſe who take the Oaths may be to blame,</hi> but he ſaith, That neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, if they act according to their Conſciences, there can be no ground for Separation, unleſs it be Lawful to ſeparate from all ſuch, who follow the Dictates of an erroneous Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and ſo there will be no end of Separation. And indeed at this rate, there will be no end of Trifling and Sophiſtry: For if I am bound to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from ſome erroneous Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, Why muſt it needs be Lawful to ſeparate from all? Have all er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous Conſciences an equal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence on Communion and good Manners? If a Man was perſwaded, that the Elements of Bread and Wine, after Conſecration were really Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiated into that very Body and Blood of Chriſt, which ſuffered on the Croſs; and accordingly ſhould in Conſcience adore it, and think all others bound to do ſo too. I have ſo much Charity for our Author, as to think he would not joyn in Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with him: And if I had to do with one, who ſcrupled eating Fleſh on <hi>Fridays,</hi> I deſire our Author to give me a good Reaſon, Why I ſhould forbear Communion with him on that account? So that after all, it is, not the erroneous Conſcience, but the nature of the Thing wherein Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence errs; which, according as it affects Communion, either requires a Separation, or allows a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:43527:2"/>
of Communion. And of which nature the Matter in Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy is, ſhall be preſently conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and then perhaps I may help him to imagine (though he ſaith he cannot at preſent) why, <hi>Becanſe ſome Mens Conſciences</hi> are ſo tender in the point of Loyalty, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not take the Oaths, that they muſt needs be ſo tender too as not to joyn Communion <hi>with thoſe who do it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But he ſaith he will leave general Reflections, and apply himſelf to the main point; and I am very glad we ſhall come to it, for here I intend to cloſe with him. The grand Queſtion he makes to be this; <hi>Whether there be any Reaſon for theſe Scruples about the Oaths?</hi> and then infers, <hi>That if there be not, it will be granted that there can be no Reaſon for a Separation on the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of them:</hi> And then proceeds, <hi>That if there be any Reaſon, it muſt ariſe, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the continuing Obligation of the former Oaths, or from the nature of the preſent Oaths.</hi> I wiſh he had told us what he means by Scruples, and what the Scruples are; for we commonly account Scruples to be odd trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome things, which proceed from a Mind well inclined, but a weak Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, not able to ſupport it ſelf, whereby men are deſirous to do well, but ſtrangely timorous and over fearful of the lawfulneſs of every thing they go about. So that at firſt daſh he repreſents all the Non-Swearers to be, at beſt, only a Parcel of well meaning Fools. For my own part, I have no Scruples, but am well ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, without any Scruple, that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not lawfully take the Oaths. And though this Author writes as trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantly as if he had the Reaſon, Senſe and Conſcience of all Mankind in his keeping, yet am I ſo nnfortunate as to think my Foundation unſhaken. But, before I can proceed, I muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form you, that he hath not fairly and truly ſtated the Caſe. For the Queſtion is not nakedly and ſimply, whether the Oaths may or may not be lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken; (though I will diſcourſe that with him in fit place) but whether Oaths impoſed under ſuch unjuſt and mercileſs Penalties, and attended with ſuch fatal Conſequences, will not war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant the Non-takers in a Separation from ſuch as do. And to clear up this, I muſt crave leave to open the Caſe more fully.</p>
            <p>After ſix Months Warning, &amp; frequent Rabling, if we take not the Oaths, <hi>we are ſilenced</hi> for ſix Months more; ſo that if the Oaths be not taken, all the Churches in <hi>England</hi> muſt be ſhut up. I know not any conſiderable difference betwixt this and a <hi>Popiſh Interdict;</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matters it much, whether we lie at the mercy of the <hi>Pope</hi> or a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whether God ſhall be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in the Land, or not. This time being elapſed, and the Oaths not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, then are we abſolutely deprived, and not only our legal Eſtates taken away, and our Wives and Children ſent to wander like Vagabonds, and beg their Bread; but our Flocks ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from us, and we not ſuffered to diſcharge our Duties towards God and his Church, and the Souls com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to our Care, which our Orders and Inſtitution enable us to, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire from us: And when, without taking the Oaths, we are not ſuffered to diſcharge our Duties, nor act in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43527:3"/>
any Communion as Miniſters, I deſire to know, what this wants of being made a Condition of Communion to us, <hi>quatenus</hi> Miniſters.</p>
            <p>But perhaps he will ſay, That we are not hereby forced to break Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, but may ſtill joyn in the ſame Communion as Lay-men: I thank him kindly; when ſome men have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed their Conſciences for large Preferments, that they may enjoy them quietly, we muſt part with all, and our Miniſtry to boot. But though this may ſerve their turn, it will not ours; for if no Lay-power can make or unmake a Biſhop, Prieſt or Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, then the Charge of our Miniſtry will ſtill lie upon us, notwithſtanding this depriving Act, and neceſſity will lie upon us to diſcharge it at our Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril. To this end I would deſire this learned Author to tell me, whether he takes us for <hi>Baal</hi>'s Prieſts, or <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi>'s Prieſts, or <hi>Parliament</hi> Prieſts, or <hi>Convention</hi> Prieſts, or <hi>God</hi>'s Prieſts: If he will, with <hi>Eraſtus,</hi> throw all into the Civil Power, I have nothing to do with him, nor any more to account of him than as one of the common Herd: But if he thinks the Power of the Clergy, as Clergy, is derived from Chriſt, to whom the Father gave all Power; and to be received by a Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Authority, who received it from them, whom Chriſt ſent as the Father ſent him; and if he think that the Biſhops of the Chriſtian Church were the Succeſſors of the Apoſtles in their ordinary and ſtanding Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity for all Ages; and that they were empowered to derive Authority to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Orders of men, to exerciſe Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Offices for the Benefit of the Church, ſtill retaining the ſupream Eccleſiaſtical Authority in their own Order in their own Churches, as all Antiquity thought, and moſt ſober men ſince: Then he muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that a Clergy-man's Authority is from God; and that, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any Civil Act to the contrary, he is bound to take care of his Office, and give account of his Stewardſhip, though the moſt bitter Perſecutions attend him for ſo doing. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if they will warrant a Civil Act to diſable us from doing our Duties, they muſt excuſe us if we have theſe dreadful apprehenſions of the Account we have to give; That we endeavour to do it as we can, at our hazard, when we are not ſuffered to do it in Communion with them.</p>
            <p>And yet this is not all, for there is one thing more which ſeems unavoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to neceſſitate a Schiſm, if we are diſcharged from our Office upon ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of theſe Oaths, though the Crime will lie at their Door, not ours. Our Author has been as great a Trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of Eccleſiaſtical Orders as any man I know; but now being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſtyled a Biſhop, I hope he will prove <hi>Strenuus ſui Ordinis Aſſertor;</hi> and being he is as well ſeen in Antiquity as any man in <hi>Europe,</hi> I hope he will not quarrel me, who am only a Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter, for aſſerting that Prerogative of his Order, which genuine Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty always appropriated to it. Now in the Primitive Times, (whoſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample and Rule our Church follows) in every Church or Dioceſs, (as now called) all the inferiour Clergy were ſubject to their Biſhops; and the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of their ſeveral Churches or
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43527:3"/>
Dioceſſes were not to tranſact any Eccleſiaſtical Matter of moment and common concern, without the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of him who was <hi>Epiſcopus primae Sedis,</hi> or Metropolitan. And though ſometimes Perſecutions made fearful Squanders amongſt them, yet it was never thought to take away the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of the inferiour Clergy to their Biſhop, nor the Dependance of the Biſhops upon their Metropolitan: And if any Clerk withdrew his Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to his Biſhop, or any Biſhop denyed his Dependance upon his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitan, he was lyable to, and certainly ſtruck with the Cenſures of the Church, though he ſuffered never ſo deeply. And if either by the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity or Apoſtacy of the Clergy or People, or the Impetuoſity of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Power, a Biſhop was ſet over a Church or Dioceſs, in oppoſition to one there Canonically placed alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, or a Metropolitan placed over a Province, in oppoſition to one alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Canonically placed there, it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in courſe produced a Schiſm, and the Church was ever accounted to be with thoſe, who adhered to them, who were firſt rightly fixed; and they always were eſteemed Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, who ſided with that Biſhop or Metropolitan, who was ſet up in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. Now this is very like to be our Caſe, and is the very thing which our Author ought to have ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. For our Metropolitan, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other Biſhops, are now actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by a Secular Act Deprived: But are they Deprived by any Canons or Canonical Cenſures of the Church? Or are they Diſcharged from their Office and Truſt which God hath committed to them? Did ever any Secular Act, much leſs ſuch an Act as this, pretend to Unbiſhop and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieſt Men? I ſhall eaſily grant, That the Secular Power hath often Seized Biſhops Eſtates, and Impriſoned and Baniſhed their Perſons: But ſtill they were accounted Biſhops of thoſe Churches, and ceaſed not to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge their Duties, as their Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances would permit, and neither their Clergy nor People renounced them, unleſs they were guilty of ſuch Crimes, for which the Cenſures of the Church did Depoſe them, or the Canons <hi>ipſo Facto</hi> Deprive them. But where's the Hereſie? Where are any of all thoſe Crimes, for which theſe our Biſhops merit Depoſition? Or what juſt Cenſure of the Church hath paſſed upon them? For any thing I can ſee, if they be not Lords, they are Biſhops ſtill, and bound by their Sacred Function, and their Duty to God, to take care of their Churches; and conſequently the Clergy of their Dioceſſes, whether Swearers or Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwearers, ought to live in Subordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and Subjection to them, and the People to pay them Obedience in all Things appeartaining to God. So that if any other Biſhop be thruſt into a Church belonging to any of theſe Biſhops, he can be no other than an Intruder; and if he claim a Right to the Church, and Act in Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the firſt Canonical Biſhops, he muſt be a Schiſmatick; for both People and Clergy are bound to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to their firſt and true Biſhop, and oppoſe the other, and refuſe Communion with him. But upon our Conſtitution, we of the Clergy
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43527:4"/>
have a further Obligation to this, for we are Sworn to pay him Canonical Obedience, and therefore we muſt either oppoſe any Man, who Unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonically ſets up againſt him, or be Perjured: And this will reach to you Swearers as well as the Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwearers; and there is no way to free us from this, but either his Death, or Deſecration, or Renun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation, though this laſt was never accounted commendable in a Biſhop.</p>
            <p>But then if one be put into the place of the Metropolitan, the Schiſm will be wider and more pernicious; for both People and Clergy, and all the Biſhops of the Province (ſo that our Author himſelf is here caught in a Nooſe, and ſhall be in a ſtreight betwixt two) are bound to adhere to the firſt and true Metropolitan, and to refuſe Communion with him who ſets up againſt him; ſo that if the extravagant Penalties of this Act take place, and others be put into the Churches of the pretended De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived, of neceſſity a Schiſm muſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low: And according to the Senſe, Judgment and Practiſe, of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Church, the Church will be with us, and the Schiſm with them; and their Schiſm will be much of the contrary Nature with that of the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſts;</hi> the Terms of Communion with the one, being as much too looſe, as with the other, too ſtreight. Our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, who is old excellent at Muſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the ill Preſidents, I know will think to ſlur this by telling us Tales, how Emperors have put out Biſhops, tranſlated Metropolitans, or erected new ones and the like. But it is one thing to act in purſuance to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of the Church, and another to act againſt them; it is one thing to ſhew particular favour to a Place or Perſon, and that with the conſent of the Church; and another thing to impoſe upon the Church againſt her Laws and the Laws of God: If he have other Inſtances, I ſhall either prove that they were Unjuſt, or come not up to our Caſe, or elſe I will yield him the Cauſe.</p>
            <p>I know not whether I can be ſo apprehenſive of the Miſchiefs of Schiſm, as our Author pretends to be, but I think I dread them as much; and the more, becauſe by woful Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience it is evident to the World, that the ſad Diviſions amongſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, have rendred Chriſtianity little more than a bare Name: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I am unwilling to lay on Load, though to help the right Side. But I will immind our Author (and I am apt to think he will quickly gueſs what I mean) that there are ſome Scandalous Perſons mentioned in Antiquity, to whom I could ſo parallel a ſort of Perſons amongſt us, that ſcarce one Egg ſhould ſeem more like another; and if things are thus puſh'd on to the height, I hope whatever we ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, we ſhall not baſely deſert God and his Church, and our Duty; and though they may go clothed in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and fine Linnen, and fare Sump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly every Day, whilſt care is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken that we may be Starved, yet they muſt expect to be Pelted, and then Men will ſpeak and write their Minds freely: For in vain do you imagine, that when Men have nothing to loſe, they have any thing to fear.</p>
            <p>Whether I have ſtated the Caſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43527:4"/>
right, I muſt leave to indifferent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to judge; but if it be right then I think it is clear, That a Schiſm will be unavoidable, and that they may waſh their Hands with <hi>Pilate,</hi> but cannot wipe off the Crime. And if I have ſtated the Caſe rightly, I need not trouble my ſelf to give any An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to his Arguments, becauſe upon this State they are all beſide the Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, and nothing to the purpoſe. But becauſe under a pretence of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing againſt Schiſm, he really un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakes the defence of the Oaths, and to cover their own Perjury would make it a Crime in us not to do the ſame thing. I ſhall take ſome notice of them on that account, but very briefly, and without any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular relation to the Caſe of the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Schiſm, as to which they are Impertinent. And here I need not follow him through all his copious Eloquence, pretty Diſguiſes, variety of Reading, and ſubordinate Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. For it is apparent to any Man who hath but half an Eye, that the whole ſtreſs of his Diſcourſe is foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on this ſingle Point. That the conſideration of the publick Good doth diſſolve the Obligation of an Oath to a Sovereign Prince rightfully claiming: For this he muſt mean, if he ſpeak home to the purpoſe; and if this Foundation prove Sandy, then he hath only raiſed a ruinous Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>But to prevent ſlanderous Tongues, I muſt firſt premiſe ſome Things. Firſt, That I do think that all Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Princes are bound to have Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the publick Good, that as their Station is above all other Men, ſo their Actions are of a more publick Influence and Concern, and of all they ſhall give a more ſevere Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to God than other Men, by how much their Truſt from him is greater. Secondly, That Kings deviat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the publick Good, may be Informed, Adviſed and Admoniſhed, by proper Perſons in a fit manner; yea that in ſome Caſes they may be ſharply Reproved, perhaps it is par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly the Duty of ſome Men to do this, though at their Peril. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, That if a Lawful King command me to any thing that is Wicked, or palpably againſt the publick Good, I ought not therein actually to obey him, and that I may uſe all Lawful means to prevent ſuch Miſchief; but not by Reſiſting, or by being Injurious to the Perſon or Honour of the Prince. But then I muſt add, That no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of publick Good whaſoever can warrant us to deſtroy a Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful King, or take off the Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of an Oath, whereby we have bound our ſelves, in all things Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and Honeſt to obey him: For this were really to overturn all things, and to deſtroy the publick Good, under pretence of preſerving it. The contrary our Reverend Author undertakes to prove, which I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reflect upon without Grief; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſeems to me a Task which would much better have become an Old Committee-man or Seque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtator, than a Divine of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet after all if we ſhould grant, that he had proved it in <hi>Theſi,</hi> yet he has no where ſo much as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to prove it in <hi>Hypotheſi,</hi> and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43527:5"/>
apply it to our particular Caſe. So that in our preſent Concern no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering Perſon can be one jot the better for all his rambling Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. But to evince the Error of his main <hi>Theſis,</hi> I ſhall now offer ſome few things to conſideration, and then give a brief anſwer to ſome things, which perhaps might not otherwiſe ſeem ſo directly and fully anſwered.</p>
            <p>How Specious or Glorious ſoever any Propoſition may ſeem in the Theory; yet it ought not to be eſteemed as right or ſound, if it be impracticable, without filling the World with perpetual Troubles and Confuſions. That his Doctrine is very liable to be abuſed, I ſuppoſe he will not deny; (though, not long ſince, a Reverend Perſon did deny it to my Face;) for the greateſt part of Mankind being wicked, and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous againſt their Governors; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this pretence a ſett of Knaves, with active Fools, may at any time cry up a diſſolution or forfeiture of the Covernment, mate the beſt of Kings, and overturn any Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and we in <hi>England</hi> ought the more to be affraid of it, becauſe this pretence hath been here moſt taking and moſt miſchievous. The Publick Good hath been made the Publick Cheat, and Common Sham; and I can ſcarce remember, that I ever heard Men commonly talk loud of Publick Good, but there was miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief brewing: And I am confident, that this Scholaſtick <hi>Chimaera,</hi> (for as they uſe it, it is no other,) within the ſpace of 50 years laſt paſt, hath coſt this Nation as much Blood and Treaſure, as tolorably well improv'd to this Day might have well nigh peopled, and ſtocked half <hi>America.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, in the next place, let us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, Who ſhall be Judge of this Publick Good? If the Supreme Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor, then our Author hath all this while been in a wrong Box, and might better have held his Peace; if he will not allow it to be placed there, becauſe a ſingle Man may be corrupted or deceived: The Anſwer is eaſie, that ſo may he, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Man; for I know no ſecurity that we now have, that any Man ſhall be infallible as to Truth and Right, and immoveable as to good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Our greateſt ſafety lies in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty and induſtry, with humble Prayers for God's Grace and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance; and perhaps the beſt State either of private Perſons or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities in this Life, is to be tolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably well: and if Perſons cannot be content to enjoy that, but make it their whole buſineſs perpetually to mend it, they had beſt have a care that they do not, worſe than that reſtleſs Projector, who to make a <hi>perfect Engine</hi> would needs erect a Windmill upon a Watermill, and ſo turn'd and overturn'd, contriv'd and hewed, till he reduc'd both to a pair of Nut-cracks. But then if any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man, or body of men, and not the Soveraign Prince, be made Judge of this Publick Good, we are nothing the beter, but ſomething the worſe, for this is to ſet a Supream above a Supream. For whoſoever is Judge of the Publick Good, according to which all Men's actions are to be directed, he has <hi>really</hi> the Command
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43527:5"/>
of all Men, whatſoever another may have in Name. But after all, the matter comes to the Mobile, and every Man muſt judge for himſelf; and ſo, for ought I ſee, may tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate his Allegiance or Obedience, or turn King of himſelf, as he pleaſes. For it matters not, what really is the Publick Good; for in Practice Men muſt and will guide their Actions by what they think is ſo, whether right or wrong: For if my Oath bind me to the Publick Good, I muſt be judge what it is, or elſe I cannot anſwer the ends of my Oath in our Author's ſence, who diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charges a Subject from his Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, in caſe the Publick Good intervene between him and the Prince. Now what brave Work will this make? We have <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, Independents, Anabaptiſts, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians,</hi> and there were Church of <hi>England</hi>-Men, perhaps there are ſome few ſtill: Now let the Prince direct as he pleaſe, or let the Publick Good be what it will, it is certain that every one of theſe Parties will judge that to be for the Publick Good, which is moſt agreeable to their Scheme of Principles, and makes for their Intereſt: And what a fine task hath a Prince, to be bound at every turn, and in every thing, to pleaſe every one of theſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rties? If he do not, then cry they, the Publick Good is concern'd, and they are abſolv'd from their Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance. Miſerable Kings! Or rather Miſerable People! For at this rate, when can we be quiet or ſafe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs one of theſe Parties ſhould be ſo fortunate, as, for the Publick Good, to knock all the reſt o'th'<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head? Such is the Fruitsof this cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated Doctrine. We very well know, and 'tis not long ſince, that it was the Grand Topick exclaimed againſt, that the Pope challengeth a Power of Depoſing Princes; and indeed it is a Doctrine, turbulent, pernicious, and to be abhorred: And yet did ever any Pope pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to Deprive a Prince, but the neceſſary benefit of Chriſtianity, and the Publick Good, was made the Pretence and ground of it? And have not we extreamly mended the matter, by putting it into the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of every Subject to Depoſe his King; or at leaſt, to endeavour it to his utmoſt, in caſe he apprehends it will be for the Publick Good? For my part, I never can be a Papiſt; and yet I think, at this rate, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Princes have made an ill ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change of one Pope, for ſo many thouſands. And it is a wonder to me, how theſe Men come to be the Darlings of Kings, who upon their Principles can never be made ſure to any, but are dangerous to all.</p>
            <p>Next I deſire to know of our Author, what this Publick Good is, and where this Divine beauty dwells, whom all our <hi>Knights Errant</hi> run Mad for, and fill the World with Blood and Slaughter? For in their way of diſcourſe, the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good is generally made a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate fine thing in the Abſtract; a ſeperate inviſible Being, diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from all perſonal intereſt and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43527:6"/>
Now if this Publick good be good for no Body, he may keep it to himſelf for me, if the reſt of his mad crew will permit it: But if Publick good be more than an airy Notion, and really prove to be a perſonal good, and that which makes for the Walfare of every one in the Community, then I am willing to put in for my ſhare; and I think every Man hath, or ought to have, a ſhare; and Kings the greateſt of all. And if we leave off theſe nice thin Diſtinctions, and ſuffer Publick Good to be (as it ought) for the ſake and benefit of Perſons; then we ſhall find, that ſhe is a moſt ſweet natur'd Creature, that doth good to all; and if at any time by chance, ſhe ſeem to have done any particular Perſon an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſs; yet one way, or other, ſhe abundantly makes him amends for it. But Alas! ſuch a Publick Good would do our Author's Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument no ſervice; for this Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good would never have taught us to Depoſe a Rightful King, to loſe our Trade, our Men, our Money, and bring our ſelves under the juſt apprehenſion of thoſe dreadful Judgments, which a People ought to expect, who have rebell'd againſt <hi>God</hi> and Man. The deſtroying the <hi>Community</hi> for the <hi>Publick Good,</hi> is a thing that paſſeth my Underſtanding.</p>
            <p>Further, I deſire our Author to inſtruct me, whether the <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good</hi> be not only conſiſtent with manifeſt Injuſtice and Wrong, but alſo an encouragement, and ſufficient Warrant, for Men to do that which is palpably unjuſt and wrongful? If he do not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffirm this, then his Publick Good doth him no Service, becauſe it comes not up to our caſe; and if he do affirm it, then I deſire him to acquit St. <hi>Paul</hi> from Preaching falſe Doctrine, when he tells us, That <hi>their Damnation is juſt, who ſay they may do evil, that good may come of it.</hi> And a ſhame take thoſe ſilly Heathen <hi>Athenians,</hi> who rejected the Counſel of <hi>Themiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,</hi> be-cauſe <hi>Ariſtides</hi> made this report of it to them, that it was indeed <hi>profitable to the Common-Wealth, but not honest:</hi> had they been Chriſtians, they might ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily have got over ſuch a pitiful Scruple; and a learned <hi>Doctor,</hi> nay <hi>(God</hi> be merciful to us) a <hi>Biſhop</hi> (commonly ſo ſtiled) of our <hi>Church,</hi> would have taught them, that the Publick Good ſanctified all, and that we ought to boggle at nothing to procure it. <hi>When, O Lord, ſhall be we delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from theſe mortified Hipocrites, who faſt for ſtrife and debate, and make long Prayers for Pretences, whilſt like Locuſts they devour all the good of the Land?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Publick Good is a very honeſt, harmleſs thing in its ſelf, but, as uſed of late, hath done a World of miſchief; and now, I think, our Author is improving it to the height, to make it diſſolve
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43527:6"/>
the obligation of Oaths, which are the moſt Sacred Tye can be laid on Man; and yet at the ſame time he deſtroys the obligation of thoſe very Oaths he perſwades Men to take: For if Men ſhould think it for the Publick Good to recal their <hi>Lawful Prince</hi> upon ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt terms; What would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the obligation of his new Oaths? And indeed in his ſenſe, all Oaths to the <hi>Supreme Governor</hi> are not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Eluſory, a mocking both of <hi>God</hi> and Man, but miſchievous and deſtructive of the <hi>Publick Peace:</hi> For he grants, that the End and Deſign of admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring ſuch Oaths, is to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the <hi>Subject</hi> to the <hi>Prince;</hi> and certainly the <hi>Publick Good</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> requires, that in all honeſt ways they be faſt to him: But if the <hi>true and juſt meaſure</hi> (as he calls it) of the obligation of theſe Oaths be the <hi>Publick Good,</hi> ſo that they bind a Man to purſue that, though to the deſtruction of the Perſon to whom they Swear, they are ſo far from being a ſecurity to him, that upon the <hi>Plea</hi> of <hi>Publick Good</hi> they may be ſet up as a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, yea as an obligation to Rebel againſt him. At this rate every Oath will be dangerous and ſeditious; and it would be the wiſdom and ſafety of the <hi>Prince</hi> never to ſuffer any to be adminiſtred. Even thoſe he calls <hi>Political Oaths</hi> were ever intended as a <hi>Perſonal Security,</hi> and ever thought ſo, and the <hi>Publick Good</hi> requires they ſhould be ſo; but, in our Author's ſenſe, they never can be ſo. And it is ſomewhat ſtrange to me, that he who has deſpiſed, all ſorts of <hi>Perſons,</hi> as ignorant and ſilly, in reſpect of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſef, ſhould now endeavour to perſwade us, that all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind has ever been ſo cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning as to Swear in his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted Metaphyſical No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>I as heartily deſire the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good as any Man, and think it every Man's duty in his Station, and to his Power to promote it; but I think it never can be done by expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>Kings;</hi> and that rather it is againſt the Publick Good by violence to oppoſe the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Governor,</hi> much more to Dethrone him; for it is always accompanied with ſuch heart-burnings, with ſuch diſcontents and factions, with ſuch diſorders and open violence, with ſuch overturn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and unſettledneſs, with the ruin of many Families, and often with ſo much Blood and Slaughter and long Wars; that the worſt of Tyranny (which can never laſt long) were better to be born, than to ſeek a remedy againſt it by ſuch unhappy means. And
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43527:7"/>
beſides all this, the ill example of ſuch proceedings influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth Poſterity, and becomes the occaſion and promoter of Eternal Troubles, wherein the <hi>Peaceable</hi> and <hi>Good</hi> are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways the greateſt <hi>Sufferers.</hi> And ſince he thinks the <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good</hi> is ſo much advanced by the late <hi>Revolution,</hi> I deſire him to caſt up the account, and tell us how much better we now are, than we were in K. <hi>J</hi>'s Reign? For my part, I do not think ſo many loſſes, ſo great charges, ſuch threatning dangers, to be compenſated by his gaining a Biſhoprick.</p>
            <p>I grow weary of diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of a <hi>Publick Good,</hi> which is ſet up to deſtroy it ſelf. I ſhall now give a brief Anſwer to ſuch other things in the Diſcourſe, as may any way ſeem to require it, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude. To ſecure the Law on his ſide he cites <hi>Glanvil</hi> and <hi>Bracton,</hi> but forgets what St. <hi>Paul</hi> and St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid; let him take his ſhare with the Lawyers; I will venture my Soul with the Apoſtles: Nor need I Anſwer the Citation; for as I ever thought, that it was the Duty of a Sovereign Prince to his Power, not only to protect his Subjects, but to be tender of them; ſo I could never be perſwaded, that it was Lawful upon any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence whatſoever to Rebel, or countenance Rebellion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him; and, not long ſince, I am ſure this was both the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and the <hi>Law</hi> of the <hi>Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of <hi>Paſſive Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> he hath anſwered with the greateſt eaſe imaginable; for he tells us, that <hi>it is imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to this purpoſe, becauſe heve is no renouncing the Doctrine of Paſſive Obedience, or aſſerting the lawfulneſs of Reſiſtence; but the ſingle point is, Whether the Law of our Nation doth not bind us,</hi> &amp;c. Now, though I think a <hi>Divine</hi> might have made a double point of it, yet for once let it paſs. Gentlemen, you have only changed the Object of your Obedience, it may be as Paſſive as you will; but if ſome blunt Fellow were to put this into plain <hi>Engliſh,</hi> I fancy I ſhould hear him ſpeak after this manner: <hi>My Maſters, you have been all this while miſtaken as to</hi> Paſſive Obedience; <hi>for it is only a Doctrine which teacheth, or, at leaſt, leaves all Men at liberty, to be Weathercocks, to turn with every Wind, and comply with every turn; and is as good a Doctrine as any</hi> Turncoat <hi>could wiſh for.</hi> I confeſs, I did not underſtand the Myſtery be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and I think our Author has made a very ſeaſonable diſcovery if it, and I wiſh he alone may have the Honour of it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:43527:7"/>
He thinks three Objections may be raiſed againſt him out of the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of <hi>Paſſive Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,</hi> which he branches in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſeveral particulars, but ſtops all their Mouths with Publick Good; but to prevent their choaking, I have pulled it out, and left their mouths open agen, and therefore need not trouble my ſelf farther in that matter, unleſs he ſhould get another ſtopple.</p>
            <p>His compariſon of a <hi>Vow</hi> and an <hi>Oath,</hi> is nothing to the purpoſe; for who ever thought, that either a Vow or an Oath bound a <hi>Man</hi> contrary to his real Duty? The Sin in ſuch a caſe is in making them, not in break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them: But let our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor ſpeak out, and tell me, that taking an Oath of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance to a Lawful Prince, is contrary to my Duty, and then I will thank him for proving, that it is Lawful to take an Oath to him who expells him. He adds, <hi>That if Parents, inſtead of regarding the good of their Children, do openly deſign their ruine, and contrive ways to bring it about; none will ſay but that they are bound to take care of their own welfare.</hi> Now I know not what a Madman may do; but none will ſuppoſe, that a Parent in his right Wits will do thus; as it is both <hi>unnatural</hi> and <hi>unreaſonable</hi> to think, that a King ſhould contrive the deſtruction of his Subjects, without whom he hath none to Reign over, or aſſiſt him: But he ſhould have told us, that the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, in ſuch a caſe, might have taken away all the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's ſubſiſtence, and done their utmoſt endeavour to ſtarve him, or cut his throat; and no doubt but this had been an excellent Comment on the Fifth Commandment.</p>
            <p>I know not to what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he ſo labours to prove, <hi>That a Natural Equity or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Right</hi> is due to Subjects, yea even to Slaves: For who ever thought, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under Government, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamorphos'd us into Beaſts, or worſe? Whereas it has been ever judged the great advantage of the <hi>reaſonable Creature,</hi> that he is both <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciable</hi> and <hi>Governable:</hi> But he ſhould have proved, that becauſe the Subject has a Common Right, therefore he can receive no wrong; or if he do, or apprehend he ſhall, then he may cry out the Publick Good, and raiſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, and overturn any Government: Nor was it kindly done to condemn Mr. <hi>Hobb</hi>'s for laying down a Propoſition, which tended to the ſecuring of Government when once eſtabliſhed in his way, when any Man may
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43527:8"/>
ſee that he hath borrow'd the worſt of Mr. <hi>Hrbbs</hi>'s Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to patch up his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; nor is there any thing material in his whole Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, but it might have been brought <hi>(mutatis mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandis)</hi> to vindicate the <hi>Long Parliament,</hi> and <hi>Oliver,</hi> and condemn K. <hi>Charles</hi> the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, and his <hi>Loyal Sufferers:</hi> But if you examine their Principles narrowly, you may obſerve that they are fitted to overturn any Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, but ſecure none; ſo that I wonder any Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can endure them, or the <hi>Men</hi> that teach them.</p>
            <p>The Caſuiſts, have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed him for allowing men under a State of Uſurpation, to do thoſe things which tend to the Publick Safety; and in another Paragraph he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers the reaſon of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure to be this; that they have not allowed them to do every thing in a State of Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation, which they might do under their Lawful Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign: But he is even with them, and roundly condemns them all for founding it <hi>on the preſumptive conſent of the abſent Prince;</hi> but it is his own miſtake; for quite contrary they found the preſumptive Conſent of the abſent Prince upon the Publick Good, and his deſire of the preſervation of his Subjects; and Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon, Obl. Conſ. Prael.</hi> 5. over whom he ſeems pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly in this place to inſult, gives this reaſon of the Prince's preſumptive will: <hi>Ejuſmodi obſequio, non tam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſte dominanti, quam toti com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitati, hoc eſt, Reipublicae ſerviiſſe exiſtimandus eſt; quam ſalvam eſſe, juſti haeredis ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilo minus intereſt, quam illius qui de facto in eâ dominatur. Fortaſſe an &amp; multo etiam ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis, quo ſincerius patriam dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere cenſendus eſt, &amp; ei omnia bona velle, qui genuinus Pater Patriae eſt, quam quo eo excluſo in ipſius aedes ſe ingeſſit, &amp; in familiam ipſius jus &amp; Imperium exercet,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I do not remember any thing more in his diſcourſe material, except <hi>a numerous heap of Inſtances,</hi> and in the Van comes the Unfortunate <hi>Vortigern,</hi> whom his Nobles forſook for endeavouring to bring in a Forreign Power: But if that be a ſufficient diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of Subjects Obligation to their Prince, as he tells us, and they thought, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to perſwade us to be of the ſame mind; I believe <hi>Some-Body</hi> will give him no thanks for it. To run through all his Inſtances would be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly troubleſome, and therefore I will make ſhort work of them; for what a miſerable ſtreight had this <hi>Great Man</hi> been reduced to,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43527:8"/>
if a wicked World and the madneſs of the People had not furniſhed him with In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of ſtrange Diſorders, Irregularities, and miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous overturnings of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment? But when thoſe very Inſtances ſhew us the Confuſions, Calamities, and Miſeries, which attend ſuch doings; to make them the Rule and Meaſure of our Actions, is to be madder than Madmen, and to take away all hopes of ever arriving at any ſettled and firm eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But what can we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect better from a Man, who lays aſide all his Divinity for a little bad Law, and worſe Hiſtory?</p>
            <p>He is ſo elevated with his laſt Inſtance, about the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of our Saviour, of paying Tribute to <hi>Tiberius;</hi> that in zeal he cannot forbear to call the Non-ſwearers perjur'd and Apoſtates.</p>
            <p>Some men ſurely, are not only privileged, but admired, for ſpeaking Contradictions. But to be ſhort, I think the the teſtimony of <hi>Velleius Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terculus</hi> concerning the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of <hi>Tiberius,</hi> to be better than our Author's, though he ſo ſcornfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject him; and I could wiſh, that if it had been but for the ſake of <hi>Dio</hi>'s reaſon, that ſome others had imitated the Wiſdom he commends in <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> in declining the impoſition of Oaths. He boaſts what he had gained upon the account of the <hi>Jews</hi> paying <hi>Tribute,</hi> but it will impoſe upon none but Fools and Partizans; and I will give it no particular anſwer, becauſe he miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents the caſe both of the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Tiberius;</hi> as to which I will only mention ſome few particulars, and then let him reckon his gains. Firſt, <hi>That none ſhould rule over the</hi> Jews, <hi>but one of their Brethren, was deſigned as a Bleſſing, if they continued in Obedience, and an encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to do ſo; ſo their being given up to a Foreign Power was a Judgment, and Curſe upon them for their Sins; and which had not befallen them but for their wickedneſs.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>That they were under a State of Conqueſt, and that to ſuch a Power, as they were no way able to oppoſe.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>That the Queſtion to our Saviour was not concerning</hi> Oaths <hi>but</hi> Tribute, <hi>which, he himſelf grants, all Caſuiſts do allow may be paid even to an Uſurper.</hi> Fourthly, <hi>That at that time no Man had</hi> Jus potius, <hi>nor had there been any prior Oaths taken in Bar againſt</hi> Tiberius; <hi>ſo that though he calls him an Uſurper, I know not where he will find one with a better Title.</hi> And by this it appears,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43527:9"/>
that our Saviour gave not the leaſt encouragement to take contradictory Oaths; and I think our Author might have been better imployed, than thus to attempt to faſten ſuch a ſcandal upon the Great Preacher of Righteouſneſs, and Saviour of the World: But I forbear too, though I ſcarce know how a Man can, in ſuch a caſe; for many rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons I am unwilling to judge ſeverely of my Brethren, who have ſworn; nor hath any Man been more forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; yet ſince he ſo boldly accuſeth thoſe, as Men of much greater Heat than Judgment, who call it Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury; I will let paſs their heat, and interpoſe for their Judgment, and if I may have liberty to Write, I will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to prove it ſo; and if I fail in the Judgment of my Biſhop and Metropoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, then to ſubmit to any Cenſure he ſhall inflict upon me. To conclude, the Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries are all run mad, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come more ungovernable than the <hi>Poſſeſſed</hi> in the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt, and daily increaſe.; and I ſee not how a Schiſm in the Church of <hi>England</hi> can be avoided, if theſe Oaths be impoſed. We have made wiſe work of it, and the <hi>Lord have Mercy upon us.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
